this
is a computer
or at least back in the 1930s 40s and
50s the person operating it was a
computer you see back then a fully
automatic calculator like this one was
mind-blowing allowing people to add
subtract multiply and divide large
numbers without the use of pen and paper
these days that's all done
electronically but when richard a local
fan reached out and said hey i've got
one of these
we jumped at the chance to become the
very thing we love the most
computers thanks to signalrgb for
sponsoring this video signalrgb is a
free application that syncs rgb lighting
across your entire setup and works for
brands like corsair razer logitech and
more check it out at the link down below
[Music]
when i was in school teachers would
insist we learned to do long division by
hand because you're not going to be
going around carrying a calculator
everywhere you go well joke's on you
miss parsons cause now everyone is doing
exactly that and trust me this baby does
long division but back in the 90s miss
parsons could be forgiven for thinking
that pocket calculators wouldn't be as
ubiquitous today seeing as many older
folks back then may have grown up with
something a lot more like this the
frieden stw10. if we were to go back
another 30 years there's a good chance
we'd find one of these chunky boys on an
accountant's desk in fact you may have
already seen something like this either
online or in a stirring historical drama
like hidden figures no it's not a
typewriter although it does sort of
share some similarities there's a
sliding carriage on top and a large set
of keys on the body but these are all
numbers and there's no ink or paper
needed at least not any that you insert
into the machine itself the first set of
mechanical number displays on the
carriage is the accumulator row which
can display results up to 20 digits long
for reference most pocket calculators
today only display around 8 or 10 and my
phone can enter up to 15 digits before
it starts using exponents the row below
that is the counter register it serves a
couple of different functions just like
how our new indoor sweater from
lttstore.com keeps you warm and boosts
your confidence don't quote me on that
the first function is how it acts as an
item counter when adding or subtracting
and the second is operations counting
when multiplying or dividing you can
lock these rows or clear them with some
button presses
or you can use one of these guys down
here to set where the decimal starts for
division i want to start it
there now down here
one numpad would be bush league so we
got two
this little one over here is used only
for entering multiplicands more on that
later and the big one is used for
everything else each digit has its own
column and you enter your total value by
pushing down keys as they would appear
on paper so for example for 1337 we push
them in order like this
one three three seven if any column has
nothing pressed that counts as zero it's
a little confusing at first but you get
used to it pretty quickly everything is
housed in a shell made of what we think
is aluminum covered in plastic that's
pretty easy to take off and there's a
giant pad of foam underneath to keep
this mechanical beast from shaking your
table to death
i mean this thing is heavy
oh
i'm doing math
i feel smarter
you can see on the inside it's basically
a giant mishmash of gears levers springs
and arms
it's like mechanical spaghetti in there
it is incredibly complex and the amount
of engineering that went into something
like this is absolutely insane there
were earlier models like the 1941
frieden h8 but these were often limited
to addition and subtraction and weren't
driven electronically the stw10 came out
a few years later and gave simple
computers
like us the ability to multiply and
divide big numbers easily hey
what do you say we crunch some numbers
so to add you enter a value on the main
pad and add it to the top row like this
bam now we enter whatever number we want
to add to that number by entering new
values and pressing the add button again
so what it's actually doing is setting a
value on a number of dials and then
ticking everything up by the new value
in sequence it's a lot like how you
would do paper math adding each digit
until there's an overflow then adding
the overflow to the end if we want to
subtract it's basically doing the exact
opposite by starting with a value and
then decreasing it in sequential order
by the new value
multiplication works in a similar way
it's basically just addition in groups
except this time we get to use the cool
multiplicand numpad i've been waiting so
long
this one actually works like what you'd
see in a modern calculator where you
enter each digit serially from left to
right and it brings up your value on
this little display here next we enter
our multiplier on the big numpad
press the mult key
and look at it go
ha
ha that is so cool we'll get some
slow-mo footage but as it's going you
can basically watch it in real time
working through the numbers brute
forcing addition of our multiplicand as
many times as i've told it to because
again i am
the computer division is basically the
same thing but backwards like
subtraction enter your first number on
the big keypad
[Music]
set your decimal place
and hit enter divd
[Music]
this puts the carriage to where it needs
to go according to our decimal point
clear the keyboard if it didn't
automatically
and enter your divisor on the same
keypad
now we're gonna have to hit both
of these divide keys we'll get to why
there are two in a moment but for now
look at it go
oh
man that never gets old just like
hitting that subscribe button never gets
old we've got our eyes on an antique or
a mechanism video in the future that you
don't want to miss now for the most part
this should just work it crunches
through the numbers to the nearest
decimal point and gives us our result
which is uh uh give me a second
33.3
repeating of course but if you were to
accidentally divide a number by zero the
machine can get stuck in an infinite
loop
what
back in the 40s and 50s if a room of
accountants or something was using
automatic calculators without this handy
div stop function we have right here
there'd actually be a guy in the room
whose job it was to basically just
listen for this infinite loop and walk
around resetting machines
now this bad boy is pretty well lubed
thanks to richard did you lube it up
oh yeah but rapidly moving metal moving
for a long time gets really hot so if
there was no button or no button man
you'd find out what was at the end of
that infinite loop molten destruction
at this moment you're probably screaming
at me at the top of your lungs riley why
does this have two division buttons why
i'm gonna need you to calm down by the
time division and multiplication were
added someone else had already beaten
frieden to the punch and patented a
single button division system preventing
freedom from including it in this model
if you press only the left division
button the division will take place but
you'll get only the tens complement of
the expected result now the stw10 was
only designed to do addition subtraction
multiplication and division but some
masters of the universe actually figured
out how to get square roots on this
thing how you ask
wizardry
uh
dining so in order to actually do a
square root on a calculator like this
you have to follow a number of different
types of algorithms to actually do it
these machines don't have a push square
root button but math has developed
algorithms that you can use to quickly
calculate a square root on a machine
like this or on paper or anywhere else
for this machine the algorithm that
we're looking at using is the sum of odd
squares for our sake it works i'll take
you through the steps of how it works
for
this 69 420. first up you move your
carriage
all the way over
and make sure that it's aligned with the
tenth digit of your number then you
enter
plus five times
now clear off and move the carriage
all the way over now we'll go through
and actually get into the weeds of
calculating this number out you put a
five
in the next column over this is the
column we're actually calculating one
and you start subtracting away
as we're going through each increment
we're essentially adding another one of
the odd numbers through some math magic
but as we're subtracting away subtract
one
subtract
two that's when you know that's the
number you're looking for you add it
back
shift the carriage
over one shift the five over one
and start again and this is where it
starts getting
a little bit repetitive
but it works
there's another underflow
add it back
clear the five move it over
shift the carriage
and again
underflow
add it back
clear the five move it over
shift the carriage
and subtract
underflow
back
and repeat
in this particular algorithm we're
breaking it up by individual digit
similar to like what you do on paper so
we're starting with the biggest number
and slowly shifting our way down as we
move on and that's an easier way to try
to handle numbers that are five plus
digits long especially for a square root
and
now that we're on this last line we
can't move the five over anymore but we
just cleared off shift over the carriage
and do the same step again just without
the extra five
and now we've done the square root but
where's the answer we have a whole bunch
of different numbers on the board for
this it's actually the board itself we
have two
six
three
point
four seven
six
seven
five
four
one
so this kind of shows the power of you
know interesting approaches to trying to
solve calculations that used to take
minutes hours days in an order of
magnitude less time how long would that
take you to do on fan paper
i'd have to learn how to do it on pen
and paper first
so what happened to calculators like
this well frieden sold thousands of
these things primarily to accounting and
insurance companies and then ended
production of the stw10 in 1966 as the
ec130 a transistor calculator with a 13
digit capacity started taking over
frieden was bought out by singer known
primarily for their sewing machines at
the time and eventually died off in the
70s as pocket calculators like this one
hit the market i mean as awesome as this
absolute unit is it's pretty obvious why
these started winning out twelve
thousand eight hundred and seventy two
multiplied by four thousand three
hundred and seven and go
yeah uh sorry frieden uh
still love ya
if you want to try and buy one of these
and try and restore it yourself they
seem to go from anywhere between two and
five hundred dollars if you can find one
you'll also be lucky if yours arrives in
perfectly working condition if you want
any tips on restoring or using them make
sure to check out richard on twitch
twitch.tv
scrobotasaurus we'll have that as well
as any affiliate links down below thanks
to bessie footwear for sponsoring
today's video bessie footwear is known
for being lightweight easy to pack
comfortable and most importantly water
resistant designed to keep you moving
bessie released their new everyday move
shoes they've got enhanced breathability
and added support making the style
perfect for the adventurous or those
looking for something sportier they've
got a pull tab to make taking them off
and putting them on super easy vegan
suede lace cages extra midsole
cushioning and the same water resistant
dymatech technology that you would find
in other vessy shoes you're going to
want to wear them everywhere the dual
climate knit material keeps your feet
warm during the winter and cool during
the summer so why wait stay dry and get
your vessy shoes today at vesey.com
linus tech tips you'll even get 25 off
using code linus tech tips at the
checkout thanks for watching everyone if
you enjoyed this video make sure to
check out our model m video the greatest
keyboard of all time reborn in which
linus stole my jacket and now i have it
back
screw you man